Hi. My name is Marwa, and I'm an architect.
مرحبا. اسمي مروة، وأنا مهندسة معمارية.
I was born and raised in Homs,
ولدت ونشأت في مدينة حمص،
a city in the central western part of Syria,
مدينة تقع في غرب منتصف سوريا،
and I've always lived here.
لقد عشت هنا طيلة حياتي.
After six years of war,
بعد ست سنوات من الحرب،
Homs is now a half-destroyed city.
حمص هي الآن مدينة نصف مدمرة.
My family and I were lucky; our place is still standing.
أنا و عائلتي محظوظون لأن بيتنا ما زال قائما.
Although for two years, we were like prisoners at home.
على الرغم من أننا عشنا لمدة عامين، مثل السجناء في الداخل.
Outside there were demonstrations and battles and bombings and snipers.
خارج المنزل ،كانت تشتعل المظاهرات والمعارك و كان هناك قصف و قناصة.
in the old town main square.
في الساحة الرئيسية للبلدة القديمة.
It's gone, as is most of the old town itself.
لقد دمر،كما هو حال البلدة القديمة نفسها.
are now rubble.
هي الآن تحت الأنقاض.
Since the ceasefire in late 2015,
منذ وقف إطلاق النار في أواخر عام 2015،
large parts of Homs have been more or less quiet.
باتت أجزاء كبيرة من مدينة حمص هادئة نوعا ما.
The economy is completely broken, and people are still fighting.
لقد تدمر الاقتصاد تماما، ومازال الناس يناضلون.
The merchants who had stalls in the old city market
التجار الذين كانوا يملكون محالا في سوق المدينة القديم
now trade out of sheds on the streets.
أصبحوا الآن يتاجرون في أكواخ في الشوارع.
Under our apartment, there is a carpenter,
تحت بيتنا، هناك نجار،
sweetshops, a butcher, a printing house, workshops, among many more.
بائع حلوى، جزار، مطبعة، ورشات عمل و غيرها الكثير.
I have started teaching part-time,
لقد بدأت التدريس بدوام جزئي،
and with my husband, who juggles several jobs,
ومع زوجي، الذي بات يمارس عدة وظائف،
we've opened a small bookshop.
استطعنا فتح مكتبة صغيرة.
Other people do all sorts of jobs to get by.
يقوم الأشخاص الآخرون بكل أنواع الأعمال ليواصلوا الحياة.
What has led to this senseless war?
ما الذي أدى إلى هذه الحرب التي لا معنى لها؟
Syria was largely a place of tolerance,
كانت سوريا إلى حد كبير مكانا للتسامح،
historically accustomed to variety,
والتعايش بين أعراق عدة عبر التاريخ،
accommodating a wide range of beliefs, origins, customs,
كانت تستوعب مجموعة كبيرة من المعتقدات والأصول والعادات،
goods, food.
و السلع و أنواع الطعام.
How did my country --
كيف لبلدي--
a country with communities living harmoniously together
هذا البلد الذي لطالما ضم مجتمعات كانت تعيش معا بانسجام
and comfortable in discussing their differences --
و تناقش فيما بينها بأريحية كل خلافاتها--
how did it degenerate into civil war, violence, displacement
كيف تدهور الحال إلى حرب أهلية، وعنف وتهجير
and unprecedented sectarian hatred?
وإلى كراهية طائفية غير مسبوقة؟
There were many reasons that had led to the war --
هناك العديد من الأسباب التي أدت إلى الحرب--
social, political and economic.
أسباب اجتماعية وسياسية واقتصادية.
They all have played their role.
جميعا لعبت دورها.
But I believe there is one key reason that has been overlooked
ولكن أعتقد أن هناك سبب محوري واحد تم تجاهله
and which is important to analyze,
و مهم لتحليل ما حدث،
because from it will largely depend
لأنه وبشكل كبير،سنرى بناء عليه،
whether we can make sure that this doesn't happen again.
إن كنا نستطيع ضمان عدم حدوث ما قد حدث مرة أخرى.
Architecture in my country has played an important role
لعبت العمارة في بلدي دورا هاما
in creating, directing and amplifying conflict between warring factions,
في خلق وتوجيه وتضخيم الصراع بين الفصائل المتحاربة،
and this is probably true for other countries as well.
وهذا على الأرجح ينطبق على بلدان أخرى أيضا.
There is a sure correspondence between the architecture of a place
هناك نوع من التواصل بين الهندسة المعمارية للمكان
and the character of the community that has settled there.
وطابع المجتمع الذي يستقر فيه.
Architecture plays a key role in whether a community crumbles
فالعمارة تلعب دورا رئيسيا في تفكك المجتمع
or comes together.
أو تعاضضه فيما بينه.
Syrian society has long lived the coexistence
عاش المجتمع السوري فترة طويلة من التعايش
and sustainable communities.
والمجتمعات المستدامة.
They have enjoyed the true meaning of belonging to a place,
وكانوا يتمتعون بالمعنى الحقيقي للانتماء إلى المكان،
and that was reflected in their built environment,
وقد انعكس هذا على البيئة المبنية،
in the mosques and churches built back-to-back,
في المساجد والكنائس التي بنيت على جدارن مشتركة،
in the interwoven souks and public venues,
في الأسواق المتشابكة والأماكن العامة،
and the proportions and sizes based on principles of humanity and harmony.
والنسب والأحجام لتلك الأبنية بناء على مبادئ الإنسانية والانسجام.
The old Islamic city in Syria was built over a multilayered past,
لقد تم بناء المدينة الإسلامية القديمة في سوريا على ماض متعدد الطبقات،
integrating with it and embracing its spirit.
اندمجت معه و استوعبت روحه.
So did its communities.
وكذلك فعلت المجتمعات فيها.
People lived and worked with each other
يعيش الناس و يعملون مع بعضهم البعض
in a place that gave them a sense of belonging
في مكان أعطاهم الشعور بالانتماء
and made them feel at home.
وجعلهم يشعرون بأنهم في وطنهم.
They shared a remarkably unified existence.
لقد تشاركوا التعايش بشكل فريد.
gradually this delicate balance of these places has been interfered with;
تمت تدريجيا حلحلة ذلك التوازن الدقيق بين هذه الأماكن،
first, by the urban planners of the colonial period,
بداية من قبل مخططي المدن في الفترة الاستعمارية،
when the French went enthusiastically about,
عندما بدأ الاحتلال الفرنسي بحماس
transforming what they saw as the un-modern Syrian cities.
بتحويل ما اعتقده عن المدن السورية كونها غير متحضرة.
They blew up city streets and relocated monuments.
لقد دمروا شوارع المدينة ونقلوا الآثار.
and they were the beginning of a long, slow unraveling.
لقد كانوا بذلك من مهد لـفترة طويلة من الانهيار البطيء.
The traditional urbanism and architecture of our cities
كان العمران التقليدي والعمارة في مدننا
assured identity and belonging not by separation,
يضمن الهوية والانتماء لا عن طريق الفصل و العزل،
but by intertwining.
بل عبر التشابك والاندماج.
But over time, the ancient became worthless, and the new, coveted.
لكن مع مرور الوقت، أصبحت المدينة القديمة لا قيمة لها،والجديدة مبهرة.
The harmony of the built environment and social environment
تم تدمير الانسجام في البيئة المبنية والبيئة الاجتماعية
got trampled over by elements of modernity --
بواسطة عناصر الحداثة--
brutal, unfinished concrete blocks,
بكل وحشية،كتل خرسانية غير مكتملة،
neglect, aesthetic devastation,
إهمال و تدمير للعنصر الجمالي،
divisive urbanism that zoned communities by class, creed or affluence.
وانقسام عمراني قسم المناطق على حسب الطبقة أو العقيدة أو الثراء.
And the same was happening to the community.
والشيء ذاته كان يحدث للمجتمع.
As the shape of the built environment changed,
فبتغير شكل البيئة المبنية من حوله،
so the lifestyles and sense of belonging of the communities
بدأت أنماط الحياة والشعور بالانتماء للجماعات
also started changing.
بدأت أيضا تغيير.
From a register of togetherness, of belonging,
فمن سجل تجمعي،و انتماء اجتماعي،
architecture became a way of differentiation,
تحولت العمارة إلى وسيلة للتمايز،
and communities started drifting apart
فبدأت المجتمعات بالانفصال
from the very fabric that used to unite them,
عن النسج التي كانت توحدها،
and from the soul of the place that used to represent their common existence.
ومن روح المكان الذي كان يمثل الوجود المشترك فيما بينها.
While many reasons had led to the Syrian war,
في خضم وجود أسباب كثيرة للحرب السورية،
we shouldn't underestimate the way in which,
لا يتوجب علينا تقليل من أهمية كيف أنه،
by contributing to the loss of identity and self-respect,
بالمساهمة في فقدان الهوية واحترام الذات،
urban zoning and misguided, inhumane architecture
قام تقسيم المناطق الحضرية وعمارته اللاإنسانية
have nurtured sectarian divisions and hatred.
في تغذية تلك الانقسامات الطائفية والكراهية.
Over time, the united city has morphed into a city center
مع مرور الوقت تحولت المدينة الموحدة إلى مركز مدينة
with ghettos along its circumference.
بأحياء متباينة على طول محيطها.
And in turn, the coherent communities became distinct social groups,
وفي المقابل ،أصبحت المجتمعات المتماسكة مجموعات اجتماعية منفصلة ،
alienated from each other and alienated from the place.
تنفر من بعضها البعض وتنفر من المكان.
From my point of view,
من وجهة نظري،
losing the sense of belonging to a place
فقدان الشعور بالانتماء إلى مكان ما
and a sense of sharing it with someone else
والشعور بتقاسم هذا المكان مع شخص آخر
has made it a lot easier to destroy.
جعل تدمير المدينة أمراً سهلا و يسيراً.
The clear example can be seen in the informal housing system,
المثال الواضح الذي يمكن معاينته هو السكن العشوائي،
which used to host, before the war, over 40 percent of the population.
الذي كان يقطنه قبل الحرب، أكثر من 40 في المئة من السكان.
Yes, prior to the war, almost half of the Syrian population
نعم، قبل الحرب، كان يعيش ما يقرب من نصف سكان سوريا
lived in slums,
في الأحياء الفقيرة،
peripheral areas without proper infrastructure,
في مناطق دون بنية تحتية ملائمة،
made of endless rows of bare block boxes
مصنوعة من صفوف لامتناهية من صناديق خرسانية
containing people,
تقطنها شريحة من السكان،
people who mostly belonged to the same group,
ينتمون في الغالب إلى نفس الشريحة المجتمعية،
whether based on religion, class, origin or all of the above.
سواء بناء على الدين أو الطبقة أو الأصل، أو جميعها معا.
Conflict is much easier between pre-categorized areas --
إذ من السهل إشعال الصراع بين المناطق المنعزلة مسبقاً--
where the "others" live.
حيث يعيش " الآخرون ".
The ties that used to bind the city together --
الروابط التي كانت تربط المدينة معا--
whether they were social, through coherent building,
سواء الروابط الاجتماعية من خلال العمران المتماسك،
or economic, through trade in the souk,
أو الاقتصادية من خلال التجارة في السوق،
or religious, through the coexistent presence --
أو الدينية،من خلال التعايش القائم --
were all lost in the misguided and visionless modernization
كلها ضاعت في ثنايا تحديث يفتقر لرؤية و هدف واضحين
of the built environment.
للبيئة المبنية.
Allow me an aside.
واسمحوا لي أن أتوقف عند هذا.
When I read about heterogeneous urbanism in other parts of the world,
عندما أقرأ عن العمران غير المتجانس في أجزاء أخرى من العالم،
involving ethnic neighborhoods in British cities
كما في الأحياء العرقية في المدن البريطانية
or around Paris or Brussels,
أوحول باريس أو بروكسل،
I recognize the beginning of the kind of instability
فإنني أستشرف بداية نوع من عدم الاستقرار
we have witnessed so disastrously here in Syria.
كالذي شهدناه بشكل كارثي هنا في سوريا.
We have severely destroyed cities,
لقد دمرنا مدننا تماماً،
such as Homs, Aleppo, Daraa and many others,
مثل حمص، و حلب و درعا وغيرها الكثير،
and almost half of the population of the country is now displaced.
وأن ما يقرب من نصف سكان البلاد نازحون الآن.
Hopefully, the war will end,
كلنا أمل أن الحرب ستنتهي،
and the question that, as an architect, I have to ask, is:
والسؤال الذي علي أن طرحه كمهندسة معمارية ،هو:
How do we rebuild?
كيف سنعيد البناء ؟
in order to avoid repeating the same mistakes?
من أجل تجنب تكرار نفس الأخطاء؟
From my point of view, the main focus should be on creating places
من وجهة نظري، يجب أن يكون التركيز الرئيسي على خلق أماكن
that make their people feel they belong.
تجعل الناس يشعرون أنهم ينتمون لها.
Architecture and planning need to recapture
إن العمارة والتخطيط بحاجة لاستعادة
some of the traditional values that did just that,
بعض القيم التقليدية التي كانت تقوم بذلك،
creating the conditions for coexistence and peace,
بخلق الظروف المناسبة للتعايش والسلام،
values of beauty that don't exhibit ostentation,
وتقدر الجمال الذي لا يدعو للتفاخر،
but rather, approachability and ease,
بل إلى التقارب و السلاسة،
moral values that promote generosity and acceptance,
و القيم الأخلاقية التي تدعو إلى الكرم والقبول،
architecture that is for everyone to enjoy, not just for the elite,
عمارة متاحة ليستمتع بها الجميع، وليست حكرا على النخبة فقط،
just as used to be in the shadowed alleys of the old Islamic city,
تماما كما كانت هناك في الأزقة المسقوفة في المدينة الإسلامية القديمة،
mixed designs that encourage a sense of community.
بتصاميمها المختلطة التي تشجع على الإحساس بالانتماء للمجتمع.
There is a neighborhood here in Homs that's called Baba Amr
هناك حي هنا في حمص يدعى حي بابا عمرو
that has been fully destroyed.
تم تدميره بالكامل.
Almost two years ago, I introduced this design
قبل عامين تقريبا قدمت هذا التصميم
into a UN-Habitat competition for rebuilding it.
إلى مسابقة الأمم المتحدة للإسكان من أجل إعادة بنائه.
The idea was to create an urban fabric inspired by a tree,
وكانت الفكرة إنشاء نسيج حضري مستوحى من الأشجار،
capable of growing and spreading organically,
قادر على النمو و التمدد الطبيعي،
echoing the traditional bridge hanging over the old alleys,
ومعيداً صدى إنشاء الجسر التقليدي فوق الأزقة القديمة،
and incorporating apartments, private courtyards, shops,
بحيث يضم التكوين شققاً وفناءات داخلية ومحالا،
workshops, places for parking and playing and leisure,
وورشات عمل ومواقف للسيارات وأماكن للعلب والاستجمام،
trees and shaded areas.
وأشجارا ومناطق مظللة.
It's far from perfect, obviously.
بالطبع تصميمي بعيدٌ جداً عن الكمال.
I drew it during the few hours of electricity we get.
إذ رسمته خلال ساعات الكهرباء القليلة التي نحظى بها.
And there are many possible ways to express belonging and community
كما أنّ هناك الكثير من الطرق الأخرى للتعبيرعن الانتماء وحسّ المجتمع
through architecture.
من خلال العمارة.
But compare it with the freestanding, disconnected blocks
ولكن قارنوه بالكتل المنفصلة والمتباعدة
proposed by the official project for rebuilding Baba Amr.
المفترحة في المشروع الرسمي لإعادة بناء بابا عمرو.
Architecture is not the axis around which all human life rotates,
ليست العمارة هي المحور الذي تدور حوله كامل الحياة البشرية،
but it has the power to suggest and even direct human activity.
ولكنها تمتلك القدرة على اقتراح وحتى توجيه النشاط البشري.
In that sense, settlement, identity and social integration
وبهذا المعنى، فإن الاستقرار، والهوية والدمج الاجتماعي
are all the producer and product of effective urbanism.
هي في نفس الآن منتج ونتاج العمران الفعال.
The coherent urbanism of the old Islamic city
يدعو العمران المتماسك للمدينة الإسلامية القديمة
and of many old European towns, for instance,
وللعديد من المدن الأوروبيةـ على سبيل المثال،
promote integration,
إلى الاندماج،
while rows of soulless housing or tower blocks,
بينما تميل صفوف السكن أو الكتل البرجية الميتة،
even when they are luxurious,
حتى عندما تكون فارهة،
tend to promote isolation and "otherness."
إلى بث العزلة و "الغربة عن الآخرين".
Even simple things
فحتى الأشياء البسيطة
like shaded places or fruit plants or drinking water inside the city
كالأماكن المظللّة والأغراس المثمرة ومياه الشرب داخل المدينة
can make a difference in how people feel towards the place,
يمكن أن تصنع فرقاً في كيفيّة شعور الناس تجاه المكان،
and whether they consider it a generous place that gives,
فيما إذا كانوا سيعتبرونه مكاناً كريماً يمكن أن يعطي،
a place that's worth keeping, contributing to,
مكانٌ يستحق الحفاظ عليه والمساهمة فيه،
or whether they see it as an alienating place,
أم سيرونه كمكانٍ يخلق الغربة،
full of seeds of anger.
وتملؤه بذور الغضب.
In order for a place to give, its architecture should be giving, too.
ولكي يستطيع مكان أن يعطي، فعلى العمارة أن تكون قادرة على العطاء أيضا.
Our built environment matters.
بيئتنا المبنية مهمة.
The fabric of our cities is reflected in the fabric of our souls.
ونسيج مدننا منعكسٌ في نسيج أرواحنا.
And whether in the shape of informal concrete slums
وسواءٌ كان على شكل عشوائيات إسمنتية،
or broken social housing
أو سكنٍ اجتماعي سيء،
or trampled old towns
أو مدنٍ قديمة مسحوقة،
or forests of skyscrapers,
أو غاباتٍ من ناطحات السحاب،
the contemporary urban archetypes
فإن النماذج العمرانية المعاصرة
that have emerged all across the Middle East
التي نشأت عبر كامل الشرق الأوسط
have been one cause of the alienation and fragmentation of our communities.
كانت سبباً للعزلة والتقسيم في مجتمعاتنا.
We can learn from this.
يمكننا التعلم من هذا.
We can learn how to rebuild in another way,
يمكننا تعلم كيفية إعادة البناء بطريقةٍ أخرى.
how to create an architecture that doesn't contribute only
كيف نخلق عمارة لا تساهم فقط
to the practical and economic aspects of people's lives,
في الجوانب العملية والاقتصادية من حياة الناس،
but also to their social, spiritual and psychological needs.
وإنما أيضاً في حاجاتهم الاجتماعية والنفسية والروحانية.
Those needs were totally overlooked in the Syrian cities before the war.
تلك الحاجات التي تم التغاضي عنها تماماً في المدن السورية قبل الحرب.
We need to create again cities that are shared
نحن بحاجةٍ مرة أخرى لخلق مدنٍ تتشارك بها
by the communities that inhabit them.
المجتمعات التي تقطنها.
If we do so, people will not feel the need
إن فعلنا ذلك، فلن يشعر الناس أنهم بحاجة
to seek identities opposed to the other identities all around,
للبحث عن هوياتٍ مضادة للهويات الأخرى التي حولهم،
because they will all feel at home.
لأنهم جميعاً سيشعرون بأنهم في وطنهم.
Thank you for listening.
شكراً لاستماعكم.